"Which NAD+ Booster Is Best?"
So, which NAD+ boosting
supplement is best?
There’s no clear standout,
as hardly any of the preclinical
effects found in the lab
have translated into evidence
of human clinical benefit.
Perhaps, this failure is to be expected
given the complexity of NAD+ physiology,
with its juggling of multiple precursors,
production pathways, and recycling routes.
The bottom line is that it’s just too early
to say if NAD+ booster supplementation
will ever live up to even
a fraction of the hype.
Many more, larger, and longer-term studies
are necessary to establish safety and efficacy.
The problem is that because NA, NAM,
NR, and NMN are all natural products,
they can’t be patented;
so, the money for well-designed
clinical trials is not as available.
The reason there have been comparatively
more trials done on NR than NMN
is that patents were originally issued for NR
before being invalidated as unpatentable.
Perhaps blindly overloading the
system with NAD+ precursors
is not the best way to go
about NAD+ restoration.
The body seems too smart to allow such
blunt incursion to affect tissue levels.
Maybe these supplements are
just profit-making distractions
from more natural approaches.
Broadly, there are three main
ways to increase NAD+ levels.
Increasing the supply of NAD+
precursors is just the first.
The other two are having
the body make more,
by activating NAD+
synthesizing enzymes,
or have the body use less, via an
inhibition of excess NAD+ degradation.
The primary determinant of NAD+
synthesis in the enzyme NAMPT.
An abundance of NAMPT tends to
decrease with age in human muscle,
dropping steadily by about 40%
between the ages of 20 and 80.
In our liver, it drops by half.
However, age-related diseases,
such as atherosclerosis,
cancer, diabetes,
and rheumatoid arthritis,
have been found to exacerbate
NAMPT decline,
raising a chicken or
the egg question.
There’s where interventional
trials come in.
Similar NAMPT declines have been
noted in aging rats and mice.
Does boosting NAMPT help?
Increasing NAMPT or its species
equivalent increases the lifespans
of yeast, fruit flies, and rodents.
An NAMPT boost also increases aerobic
capacity and exercise endurance in mice,
in addition to helping them live longer.
Enhanced expression of NAMPT increases
the NAD+ levels in the muscles in mice
comparable to feeding them
dietary NAD+ precursors,
but if you remember,
NAD+ precursors don’t seem to be able to
affect NAD+ muscle levels in most people.
In fact, such supplements can
actually suppress NAMPT,
while boosting that methylating enzyme
to rid the body of the excess.
In addition to methyl depletion,
chronic administration
of these supplements
could potentially then leave people
worse off should they ever stop them.
There is, however, a way to naturally
boost NAMPT and NAD+ levels in humans
without any supplements: exercise.
Athletes have about twice the NAMPT
expression in their musculature
compared to sedentary individuals.
To prove cause and effect,
sedentary men and women started
a stationary bike exercise protocol,
and within three weeks, NAMPT
levels increased by 127%.
Resistance training can
also increase NAMPT,
and this can also translate into a
127% increase in muscle NAD+ levels
and a rise in sirtuin activity.
In other words,
exercise can do what NAD+
boosting supplements can’t.